Guide to the Solange Clésinger-Sand Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Solange Clésinger-Sand Papers
1834-1952
GEN MSS 755
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.43
(6 boxes)
Collection contains correspondence, writings, and other papers documenting the life and work of Solange Clésinger-Sand. Correspondence consists of letters to and from Clésinger-Sand and third-party letters between family and others. Notable correspondents include the following friends, family, and family friends: Éduoard Bourdet, Alphonse Guérin, Amélie Grille de Beuzelin, Maurice Sand, Charles Poncy, Samuel Rocheblave, and Jules Troubat. Writings by Clésinger-Sand include complete manuscripts for the early "Les roses et une fauvette..." (1834), "Histoirettes pour les toute petits," and a travelogue entitled "Une visite à Charon", in addition to a number of drafts for incomplete projects, including a play ("Sélim"), a theatrical adaptation of the novel L'Uscoque by George Sand, and a novel ("Thora"). Other materials include artwork, clippings, financial and legal records, notebooks, photographs, and papers relating to property ("Villa Malgrétout") purchased by Clésinger-Sand. Photographs include portraits of Clésinger-Sand, her husband, sculptor Jean Baptiste Clésinger, and others.
Clésinger-Sand, Solange, 1828-1899
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Amazones on the Edith and Richard French Fund, 2009, and on the Frederick W. Hilles Fund, 2012.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Solange Clésinger-Sand (1828-1899)
Solange Clésinger-Sand, daughter of prolific 19th century French author George Sand and Casimir Dudevant. Studied piano with Frédéric Chopin during Chopin's summer sojourns at the Sand estate in Nohant from the late 1830s to mid 1840s. Married sculptor Jean-Baptiste (Auguste) Clésinger in 1847. Author of two published novels, Jacques Bruneau (1870) and Carl Robert (1887). Samuel Rocheblave, biographer of George Sand, compiled the correspondence between Solange and her mother as George Sand et sa fille d'après leur correspondance inédite (1905).
Scope and Contents
The Solange Clésinger-Sand papers contain correspondence, writings, and other papers. Correspondence consists of letters to and from Solange Clésinger-Sand and third-party letters between family members and others. Notable correspondents with Clésinger-Sand include the following friends, family, and family friends: Nazli and Wacyf Azmy, Éduoard Bourdet, General Cantilli, Alphonse Guérin, Amélie Grille de Beuzelin, Maurice Sand, Charles Poncy, Samuel Rocheblave, and Jules Troubat. Writings include complete manuscripts for the early "Les roses et une fauvette..." (1834), "Histoirettes pour les toute petits," and a travelogue entitled "Une visite à Charon", in addition to a number of drafts for incomplete projects, including the play "Sélim," a theatrical adaptation of L'Uscoque, a novel by George Sand, entitled "Orio Soranzo," and a novel, [On Thora]. Writings also include manuscript notes and fragments. Other materials include artwork, clippings, financial and legal records, notebooks, photographs, and papers relating to a property in Cannes, named Villa Malgrétout, purchased by Clésinger-Sand in 1869. Photographs include portraits of Clésinger-Sand, Alfieri di Sostegno, Jean-Baptiste (Auguste) Clésinger, Charles Poncy, and Fernand de Préaulx.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1849-1899. II. Writings, 1834-1862. III. Other Material, 1852-1952.
Authors, French -- 19th century; French literature -- 19th century; Photographic prints; Authors; Bourdet, Édouard, 1887-1945; Chopin, Frédéric, 1810-1849; Clésinger, Jean-Baptiste, 1814-1883; Clésinger-Sand, Solange, 1828-1899; Grille de Beuzelin, Amélie; Guérin, Alphonse, 1816-1895; Poncy, Charles, 1821-1891; Rocheblave, S. (Samuel), 1854-1944; Sand, George, 1804-1876; Sand, Maurice, 1823-1889; Troubat, Jules, 1836-1914
- Correspondence, 1849-1899; Series I; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into two subseries for General Correspondence and Third-Party Correspondence. Arranged alphabetically by correspondent within subseries.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, contains letters to and from Solange Clésinger-Sand and third-party correspondence. Notable correspondents with Clésinger-Sand include the following friends, family, and family friends: Nazli and Wacyf Azmy, Éduoard Bourdet, General Cantilli, Alphonse Guérin, Amélie Grille de Beuzelin, Maurice Sand, Charles Poncy, Samuel Rocheblave, and Jules Troubat. In addition, copies of correspondence between Clésinger-Sand and philosopher Pierre Lanfrey can be found in Series II. Writings, "Declaration perdue!" Outgoing letters from Clésinger-Sand to others are mentioned in folder notes.
  Third-Party Correspondence consists chiefly of letters between family members and others.
  - General Correspondence
    - Alfieri di Sostegno, Adèle, [1897] (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Aubineaux, L., 1876 November 6 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Aucante, Emile, 1871-1895, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Azmy, Nazli, 1894-1899, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Azmy, Wacyf, 1890-1899, undated (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
    - Bascans, Sophie, 1854-1856 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Bennetot, ----, 1897-1898 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Bertholdi, Augustine de, 1855 January (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Bourdet, Édouard, 1851 November 10 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - [Bourdet?], Pauline, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Brétillot, Antoinette, 1885, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Bridoux, ----, 1893 November 25 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Calmann, Paul, 1894 June 21 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Calmann-Lévy (Firm), 1874-1878 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Cantilli, General, 1896-1899, undated (Box 1, Folder 16-18)
    - Cazamajou, Oscar (cousin), 1876 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Challes, Marie de, 1893 February 1 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Choiecki, [Charles] Edward, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Chopin, Frédéric, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Copies of letters from Solange Clésinger-Sand in the hand of Aurore Lauth-Sand
    - Clairin, Madame, [1898] (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Courtois, Gustav, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Delagrave, Charles, 1894, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Edmond, Charles, 1895, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Escamps, Henri, 1883, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Forsi, Adèle, 1897-1898, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Gaubert, Marie, 1897-1898 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - [Ganneval], A., [1854] (Box 1, Folder 30)
      Includes letters from Solange Clésinger-Sand
    - Garbeiron, A., undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Grille de Beuzelin, Amélie, 1856-1899 (Box 1, Folder 32-33)
    - Guérin, Alphonse, 1870, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Guerin, E., 1854 February 4 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Guerin, René, [1852?] November 24 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Haider Ali Chinassi, Fazil, 1898-1899 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Kaempfen, Albert, 1883, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Khalil-Bey, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Lambert, Madame, 1897 December 20 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Lami-Sarrazin, R., 1890, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Lanfrey, Pierre
    - Langlois, ----, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Meindre, Noémie, 1894, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Napoléon, Maison du prince, 1858 December 29 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Nencioni, Enrico, undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - [Perfetti?], Elena, 1879 February 3 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Polignac, A. de, 1855, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Poncy, Charles, 1865-1880, undated (Box 2, Folder 48-49)
    - Ravignac, H. de, 1855, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Renart, E., 1889 February 17 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Rocheblave, S. (Samuel), 1891-1898, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Rondier, ----, 1894 February 2 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Sand, Gabrielle (niece), undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Sand, Lina (sister-in-law), 1887-1899 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Sand, Maurice (brother), 1866-1888 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Simonnet, Léontine (cousin), 1889 February 12 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Simonnet, René (cousin), 1894-1896 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - [Stetten?], Carl, 1896 July 16 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Tissier, A., 1892 June 18 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Troubat, Jules, 1876, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Valdahon, Mme de, 1854 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Vallès, C., 1872-1887, undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - ----, Roger, 1882 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Others (general), 1855-1899, undated (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Others (family), 1866-1897, undated (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Envelopes, undated (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Third-Party Correspondence
    - Aucante, Emile to Ganneval, 1854 July 18 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Bascans, Sophie to Jeanne (Nini) Clésinger, 1849 July 20 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Bascans, Sophie to George Sand, 1854 May 15 (Box 2, Folder 70)
      Envelope only
    - Bethmont, [Eugene] to George Sand, 1854 December 25 (Box 2, Folder 71)
      Copy of letter in the hand of Solange Clésinger-Sand
    - Borie, Victor to [Eugene] Bethmont, 1855 January 14 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Clémenceau, A[lbert] to [Frédéric Lauth], undated (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Clésinger, Jean-Baptiste (Auguste) to George Sand, 1853, undated (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Clésinger, Jeanne (Nini) to George Sand, 1852, undated (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Coutant, M. to [Frédéric Lauth], 1899 March 24 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - "Juge de Paix" to [Frédéric Lauth], 1899 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Lauth-Sand, Aurore to unidentified, undated (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Moreau, George to [Frédéric Lauth], 1899 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Orsay, [Alfred Guillaume Gabriel] to George Sand, undated (Box 2, Folder 80)
      Copy of letter, dated 3 mai 1852, in the hand of Solange Clésinger-Sand
    - Rouchaux, Louis de to Calmann-Lévy (Firm), [18]81 April 26 (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - Sand, George to others, undated (Box 2, Folder 82)
      Copies of letters from George Sand to others, including Madame St. Aubin Deslignieres and Edme Simonnet, in the hand of Solange Clésinger-Sand
    - Simonnet, E[dme?] to Aurore Lauth-Sand, 1899 March 23 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - Others, 1899, undated (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - "Dossier sur Jeanne Clésinger (Nini)", undated (Box 2, Folder 85-87)
      Contains copies of letters relating to Nini Clésinger
- Writings, 1834-1862; Series II; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  Series II, Writings, contains drafts for poems, novels, theatrical adaptations, and other writings by Solange Clésinger-Sand. There are complete manuscripts for the early "Les roses et une fauvette..." (1834), "Histoirettes pour les toute petits," and a travelogue entitled "Une visite à Charon", in addition to a number of drafts for incomplete projects, including a play ("Sélim"), a theatrical adaptation ("Orio Soranzo") of a novel ( L'Uscoque ) by George Sand, and a novel, [On Thora]. Writings also contain notes and manuscript fragments.
  - "Arlequin muet par crainte: comedie Italienne en 3 actes...", holograph (copy), corrected, undated (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - "Campagne de bohême 1741 et 42," notes, holograph, undated (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - "Chanson des farfadets," poem, holograph, undated (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - "Chant de rouge gorge," poem, holograph, undated (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - "La conseillère le coulteux," holograph, corrected, undated (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - "Declaration perdue!", undated (Box 3, Folder 93)
    Contains copies of correspondence between Solange Clésinger-Sand and Pierre Lanfrey
  - "Les deux B...g...e (Arthur)," holograph, corrected, undated (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - "Eglogues," drafts, translations, corrected, undated (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - "Le franc archer, 1562, chanson," holograph (copy?), undated (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - "Des gens qui j'aime: le Vicomte de B.," holograph fragment, corrected, undated (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - "Des gens qui me plaisent: Henry," holograph, corrected, 1859 (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - "Guerres de Louis XV," holograph, corrected, 1860 (Box 3, Folder 99)
  - "Histoire de la Marquise S. Montbel," holograph, corrected, undated (Box 3, Folder 100)
  - "L'histoire d. Mme Tavart avec le mal d. Saxe d'apres Grimm," holograph, corrected, undated (Box 3, Folder 101)
  - "Histoirettes pour les toute petits..." holograph, corrected, undated (Box 3, Folder 102)
  - "Le J. de Venise," holograph, corrected, undated (Box 3, Folder 103)
  - "Joseph de Maistre," notes, holograph, undated (Box 3, Folder 104)
  - [Journal], fragments, undated (Box 3, Folder 105)
    Copies in the hand of Christiane Sand
  - [Notes and fragments], holograph, undated (Box 3, Folder 106-111)
  - "Notes sur les chevaux," holograph, undated (Box 3, Folder 112)
  - [On George Sand], notes, holograph, undated (Box 3, Folder 113)
  - [On Maurice Sand], notes, holograph, undated (Box 3, Folder 114)
  - [On Thora], novel (incomplete), drafts and notes, holograph, 1856-1862, undated (Box 3, Folder 115-117)
  - "Orio Soranzo," theatrical adaptation, draft, holograph, corrected, undated (Box 3, Folder 118)
  - "Pendule style Louis XVI," poem, holograph, undated (Box 3, Folder 119)
  - ["Le pere de..."], holograph, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 120)
  - "Le philosophe amoureux," drafts, holograph, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 121)
  - [Untitled poems], drafts, holograph, 1857, undated (Box 4, Folder 122)
  - "Raoul de Rion d'Amianes à son ami de Marquis de Villumes," holograph, [185?] (Box 4, Folder 123)
  - "Les roses et une fauvette dans son nid et ses petits," holograph, 1834 (Box 4, Folder 124)
  - "Le sacré coeur," holograph, corrected, 1854 November (Box 4, Folder 125)
  - "Sélim," play, holograph, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 126)
  - "Stullitae laus stullitae loquitas," holograph, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 127)
  - "Une visite à Charon," holograph, undated (Box 4, Folder 128)
- Other Material, 1842-1952; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically by material type.
  Series III, Other Material, contains artwork, clippings, financial and legal records, notebooks, photographs, and papers relating to a property in Cannes purchased by Clésinger-Sand in 1869.
  Photographs include studio portraits, with carte-de-visites and cabinet cards, and images of artwork and interiors of the Sand estate in Nohant, France. Portraits include Solange Clésinger-Sand, Alfieri di Sostegno, Jean-Baptiste (Auguste) Clésinger, Charles Poncy, Fernand de Préaulx, and others. Other photographs include an image of Auguste Clésinger's celebrated "Femme piquée par un serpent" [Woman bitten by a serpent] (1847) housed at the Musée d'Orsay.
  Material relating to Villa Malgrétout, named after the novel ( Malgrétout ) by her mother, consists of correspondence, plans, and financial and legal documents.
  - "Administration spéciale des funérailles" form, completed in manuscript by [Marguerite Marier?], 1913 October 20 (Box 4, Folder 129)
  - Artwork, undated (Box 4, Folder 130)
  - Burial wish, 1880, 1891 (Box 4, Folder 131)
  - Calendar fragments, 1875-1876 (Box 4, Folder 132)
  - Clippings, 1898-1899, undated (Box 4, Folder 133)
  - Financial records, 1855-1899, undated (Box 4, Folder 134-139)
  - Legal documents, 1855, 1888 (Box 4, Folder 140)
  - Lists, 1856, undated (Box 4, Folder 141)
  - Lock of Solange Clésinger-Sand's hair, undated (Box 4, Folder 142)
  - Notebooks, undated (Box 4, Folder 143-145)
  - Photocopies, undated (Box 5, Folder 146)
  - Photographs, 1842-1897, undated (Box 5, Folder 147-157)
    Includes photographs by Claude-Olivier Darré
  - Plant specimen, 1881 (Box 5, Folder 158)
  - Portrait of Jeanne-Gabrielle ("Nini") Clésinger, undated (Box 5, Folder 159)
    Photocopy of a drawing by her grand-mother George Sand
  - Stationary, undated (Box 5, Folder 160)
  - Villa Malgrétout material, 1870-1952 (Box 5, Folder 161-168)
  - Oversize, 1842-1952; 1.34; (1 box)
    - Artwork, undated (Box 6, Folder 169)
    - Clippings, 1898, undated (Box 6, Folder 170)
    - Financial records, 1855, undated (Box 6, Folder 171)
    - Villa Malgrétout material, 1870 June 29 (Box 6, Folder 172)